CORINA AREAS SOLIS

DATA ENGINEER

P +505 8950-3185



corinareas@gmail.com



corina.areas

QUALIFICATIONS SUMMARY

Highly ambitious Data Engineer/ Data Analyst with over 10 years of experience using management tools for Data analysis, ETL extractors, data warehouse, programming, and methodology in project development and execution, I consider myself very passionate and committed to my work. I'm Scrum certified and also a master's in business informatics.

Managing data-related projects with clients in the USA, Canada, and LATAM with the following technologies (Not Limited To):

Codeless ETL tools:

FiveTran, HevoData, Stitch, Informatica Cloud, Openbridge.

Batch ETL and Real-Time Data Streaming:

♣ SSIS, Python, Airflow On-Premise and On-Cloud (Composer), Snowpipe, DBT On-premise and Cloud, Databricks with pyspark, Redshift Streaming Ingestion. AWS Glue, Azure Data Factory, Azure Fabric, Datalake.

DWH, Databases and Query Engines:

Snowflake, PostgreSQL, Azure SQL, KQL, DAX, Synapse, MongoDB, MySQL, RDS, SQL Server, Redshift, Aurora, Athena, Hadoop, Presto, Hive, Databricks.

Cloud and Containers:

♣ GCP, AWS, Azure, MongoDB Atlas, Docker.

Project Management, Documentation, CI/CD and Source Control:

 ♣ MS Project, Jira, Azure DevOps, Trello, ASANA, Confluence, Miro, Alation, Dataedo, GitHub, GitLab, Bitbucket, CircleCI.

Data visualization:

♣ PowerBI Service and On-Premise. Tableau. Quicksight, Metabase, Cognos IBM, SAP, SSRS.

EDUCATION

Master's Business Informatics UNI, NATIONAL UNIVERSITY OF **ENGINEERING** 2013 - 2015

B.S. Systems Engineering and Information Technologies UNI, NATIONAL UNIVERSITY OF **ENGINEERING** 2006 - 2012

CERTIFICATIONS

- MICROSOFT CERTIFIED AZURE **DP900**
- AWS CERTIFIED CLOUD **PRACTITIONER**
- MICROSOFT CERTIFIED DATA **ANALYST**
- AZURE ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATE
- **SCRUM DEVELOPER**
- **DEVOPS ESSENTIALS PROFESSIONAL**
- SCRUM PROFESSIONAL
- MICROSOFT CERTIFIED AZURE AZ900
- **BUSINESS INTELLIGENCE FOUNDATION**

EXPERIENCE

July 2023 - Present

Team Leader Data Engineer | DataDevs Consulting

- ✓ Project management
- ✓ Develop data pipelines, data models and dashboards
- ✓ Objects creation, loading of information, stored procedures tasks testing, and deployment using Snowflake.
- ✓ Snowflake Data Warehouse Maintenance.
- ✓ Working with NonSQL like MongoDB Database
- ✓ Implement Star and Snowflake schemas to build enterprise data warehouses on Snowflake.
- Maintenance and development solutions end to end in Looker.
- ✓ Develop and optimization data transformations using DBT Cloud – ETL Solutions.
- ✓ CI/CD Deployments
- ✓ Experience in SQL and PostgreSQL
- ✓ Dataedo Modeling Tools
- ✓ Alation Data Catalog
- √ Tableau Developer and Designer
- ✓ Experience in developing data products using big data technologies as Hadoop, Hive and Presto
- ✓ Confluence experience
- ✓ Data transfer between AWS S3 and Snowflake DB.
- ✓ Storing semi-structured data into Snowflake Tables and make it available to users through views.
- ✓ AWS Migration

January 2020 - July 2023

Senior Data Engineer - DataDevs Consulting

- ✓ Create new and enhancing performance of dashboards using PowerBI, Apache Airflow (ETL tool), and Snowflake DWH.
- ✓ Create new and enhancing performance of dashboards using Looker, DBT Cloud (ELT tool), and Snowflake DWH
- ✓ Develop data pipelines with Python, Redis and MySQL
- Automation of data pipelines using Apache Airflow, Python, AWS S3, Snowpipe, Snowflake DWH, and DBT on-premise and DBT Cloud.
- ✓ Build data models with LookML within Looker.
- ✓ Document dashboards and data flows for both Users and the Technical team using Confluence, LucidChart and Redgate Tools.
- ✓ Data modeling with Alation, Dataedo, and Visio
- ✓ Data Integration with HevoData
- Querying Presto and Snowflake Datawarehouse, Hadoop, Hive.

SKILLS

- AGILE METHODOLOGIES (SCRUM/KANBAN)
- PYTHON
- C#
- ASP.NET
- SQL SERVER
- RDS
- NONSQL
- LOOKER
- SNOWFLAKE
- DBT CLOUD
- DAX
- AWS
- AZURE
- BI
- ETL

LANGUAGES

- ENGLISH
- PORTUGUESE
- SPANISH

September 2021 – July 2023

Senior Data Engineer | Consulting Group

- ✓ Lead different projects
- ✓ Analytical solutions using SSRS Reports
- ✓ Build Power BI Dashboards using complex DAX functions and Power Query transforms, building efficient models
- ✓ Build Solutions ETL SSIS
- ✓ Writing and troubleshooting complex SQL queries
- ✓ SSAS Solutions
- ✓ Practice Agile Methodology throughout the project lifecycle.
- ✓ Develop continuous Data Ingestion pipelines via Azure Data Factory.
- ✓ Develop Conceptual Model, Logical Model and Physical Data Model.
- ✓ Define and maintain enterprise standards for the data architecture.
- ✓ Provide training and knowledge transfer from end-to-end solutions to peers and client resources as well.
- ✓ Experience writing SnowSQL queries, Stored Procedures, Views, and User Defined Functions to Extract, Load and Transform data as per Business requirements.

January 2018 - September 2021

Data Engineer | LAFISE Group

- ✓ Project Coordinator
- ✓ Analytical solutions using SSRS Reports and Cognos BI.
- ✓ Web Application analysis and development using .Net
- ✓ Build scalable databases using SQL
- ✓ Gathering and analyzing business requirements
- ✓ Data Warehousing
- Experienced in optimization of database code designing batch processing and query tuning
- ✓ Development of ETL solutions for multi data sources.
- ✓ Team Foundation Services
- ✓ GIT
- ✓ CI/CD Deployments
- ✓ NonSQL Mainteinance
- ✓ Data modeling and report building to publish enterprise results through the Power BI.
- ✓ Azure Data Factory ETLs

September 2020 - August 2021

Professor | National University of Engineering

✓ Post Graduate Course in Power BI Advance

February 2015 - January 2018

ETL Developer | BAC Credomatic Bank

- ✓ Optimization queries improving their performance.
- ✓ Create stored procedures, functions, views, tables, index in SQL Server
- ✓ CRM management, SIEBEL, ELOQUA
- ✓ AS400, QUERY/400, and DB2 Reports
- ✓ Projects of mass mailing campaigns
- ✓ Build scalable databases using SQL
- ✓ Digital transformation management support
- ✓ Accompaniment to business areas
- ✓ Use SSIS tool to extract, transform and load (ETL) data.
- ✓ Meet with the users and collect requirements
- ✓ Get information from different data source and consolidate the information in a data warehouse using ETL techniques.
- ✓ Apply business intelligence techniques and best practices.
- ✓ Apply dimensional modeling knowledge.
- ✓ Develop new reports, support reports and fix bugs.
- ✓ Use monitoring tools, create indexes, and use best practices.
- ✓ Used workflow and process engines to compare present models and refine them to be more efficient.
- ✓ Worked with stakeholders to elicit requirements

July 2013 - February 2015

Regional Business Intelligence | The Data Age

- ✓ Analytical Solutions using SAP Desktop Intelligence
- ✓ Build Solutions ETL Unix
- ✓ Datawarehouse Solutions and Datamining
- ✓ Optimization of SQL queries in Oracle databases
- ✓ Performance in commercial systems in the energy field.
- ✓ Data warehouse management for reporting
- ✓ Development of ETL processes.
- ✓ Integration of different business data marts.
- ✓ Generation of automatic reports on servers and email.
- ✓ Automatic management of information grouping level.
- ✓ Creation of alerts for decision making.
- ✓ Development of models that simulate the billing of all customers under different rate schedules
- ✓ Projections of indicators to define future goals based on historical behavior and operations planning.
- ✓ Reduction in query response time in online applications

July 2010 – February 2011

Intern | National University of Engineering

- ✓ Web application development for Academic Magazine
- ✓ Development of many web applications to automate the business process and generate clean and accurate information needed for the managers
- ✓ Create scripts in PostgreSQL
- ✓ Design in Photoshop, CorelDraw
- ✓ Implementation of new technologies, as well as updating and adapting existing ones
- ✓ Computerize through computer software the Records of the inscriptions made by the teachers.
- ✓ Solve technical problems by writing optimized algorithms for them.
- ✓ Translate user stories into features and fix bugs